Guide to the Charles Ives Oral History Collection
Charles Ives Oral History
Oral History of American Music
Charles Ives Oral History
1968 1974
OHII
Oral History of American Music
111 Computer Files
General
70 interviews. This finding aid describes digitized copies of the interview recordings in this collection. Oral History of American Music also holds the original recordings, on a variety of legacy audio and video formats.
Scope and Contents
The Charles Ives Oral History was the first documentary oral history of an American composer. Interviews with sixty people who knew and worked with Charles Ives were conducted between 1968 and 1971, and this project was the impetus for the founding of Oral History of American Music (OHAM). Family, friends, neighbors, business associates, and musicians reminisce about one of the most significant artistic figures of the century. The project formed the basis of the award-winning book by Vivian Perlis, Charles Ives Remembered: An Oral History (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1974, and subsequently reprinted). Excerpts from the taped interviews were used in a five record package, "Charles Ives 100th Anniversary" (1974) and in a film documentary, "A Good Dissonance Like a Man" (1977).
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. The finding aid includes links to stream most interviews online via Oral History of American Music's (OHAM) AV access system, Aviary. Yale users can login to Aviary using their Yale University ID, to stream these interviews without restriction. Other users are able to request access to interviews directly through Aviary. For access instructions, and to request transcripts of an interview, see OHAM's website. This finding aid also includes links to Table of Contents for most interviews.
Some interviews may be restricted. Access to these restricted interviews may only be granted to a patron who has first obtained direct permission from the interviewee or their estate.
Some interviews may not have been digitized or are otherwise not available to stream online. However, these interviews may have been transcribed. Please see contact OHAM for more details.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by surname of interviewee.
Related Collections
MSS 14, The Charles Ives Papers.
MSS 14 HSR, Charles Ives Rare and Non-Commercial Sound Recordings.
Composers United States 20th Century; Ives, Charles, 1874-1954
- Becker, Eugene
  - Becker, Eugene, 1971 January 30; OHII 47 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 63 mins; Transcript Page Count: 22 pages
    Interview Location
    Washington, DC
    Becker, Eugene D., 1919-1978
- Becker, Mrs. John
  - Becker, Mrs. John, 1973 October 15; OHII 58 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 71 mins; Transcript Page Count: 25 pages
    Evanston, IL
    Becker, Evelyn
- Bell, Mary
  - Bell, Mary, 1970 December 10; OHII 44 a-c; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 74 mins; Transcript Page Count: 47 pages
    New York, NY
    Bell, Mary
- Berger, Arthur
  - Berger, Arthur, 1970 October 19; OHII 41 a-c; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 95 mins
    Cambridge, MA
    Berger, Arthur, 1912-2003
- Berneri, Mrs. Samuel
  - Berneri, Mrs. Samuel, 1972 March 23; OHII 56 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 59 mins; Transcript Page Count: 41 pages
    Conditions Governing Access
    This material is restricted. Access may be granted to a patron who has obtained direct permission from the interviewee or their estate.
    Berneri, Louise Garbarino, 1906-1993
- Bronson, Louis
  - Bronson, Louis, 1969 July 28; OHII 18 a; Maas, Martha, 1934-; Approximate Running Time: 28 mins; Transcript Page Count: 13 pages
    New Haven, CT
    Bronson, Louis Henry
- Buesing, Charles
  - Buesing, Charles, 1969 September 1; OHII 21 a; Maas, Martha, 1934-; Approximate Running Time: 32 mins; Transcript Page Count: 15 pages
    Buesing, Charles
- Carter, Elliott
  - Carter, Elliott, 1969 June 20; OHII 14 a-c; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 80 mins; Transcript Page Count: 40 pages
    Waccabuc, NY
    Carter, Elliott, 1908-2012
- Copland, Aaron
  - Copland, Aaron, 1970 January 30; OHII 31 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 21 mins; Transcript Page Count: 17 pages
    Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990
- Deutsch, Nina
  - Deutsch, Nina, 1974 May 21; OHII 59 a; Sherman, Robert; Approximate Running Time: 51 mins
    Recording missing
    No CD or digital file for this interview could be found in Feb 2019 when reviewing this interview's metadata.
    Deutsch, Nina
- Engel, Lehman
  - Engel, Lehman, 1969 October 12; OHII 27 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 32 mins; Transcript Page Count: 19 pages
    Engel, Lehman, 1910-1982
- Farr, Charles
  - Farr, Charles, 1970 September 10; OHII 39 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 12 mins; Transcript Page Count: 17 pages
    Farr, Charles
- Flexner, James
  - Flexner, James, 1970 December 11; OHII 45 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 22 mins; Transcript Page Count: 40 pages
- Fraser, Peter
  - Fraser, Peter, 1969 November 21; OHII 30 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 50 mins; Transcript Page Count: 29 pages
    Hartford, CT
    Fraser, Peter
- Grey, William
  - Grey, William, 1970 November 11; OHII 43 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 15 mins; Transcript Page Count: 9 pages
    Redding, CT
    Grey, William
- Hall, Arthur
  - Hall, Arthur, 1971 March 22; OHII 48 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 55 mins; Transcript Page Count: 34 pages
    Houston, TX
    Hall, Arthur
- Harrison, Lou
  - Harrison, Lou, 1970 March 24; OHII 36 a-d; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 129 mins; Transcript Page Count: 74 pages
    Aptos, CA
    Harrison, Lou, 1917-2003
- Hatch, Harold A.
  - Hatch, Harold A., 1970 September 10; OHII 38 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 19 mins; Transcript Page Count: 10 pages
    Sharon, CT
    Hatch, Harold Ames
- Herrmann, Bernard
  - Herrmann, Bernard, 1969 November 12; OHII 29 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 63 mins; Transcript Page Count: 50 pages
    Herrmann, Bernard, 1911-1975
  - Herrmann, Bernard, 1969 February 11; OHII 29 c; Approximate Running Time: 53 mins
    Santa Barbara, CA
    Interviewer
    Lecture on Charles Ives
- Hofmann, George
  - Hofmann, George, 1969 September 13; OHII 23 a-c; Maas, Martha, 1934-; Approximate Running Time: 97 mins; Transcript Page Count: 39 pages
    Hagaman, NY
    Hofmann, George F.
- Ives, Bigelow
  - Ives, Bigelow, 1969 March 12; OHII 7 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 45 mins; Transcript Page Count: 25 pages
    Danbury, CT
    Ives, Bigelow
- Ives, Brewster
  - Ives, Brewster, 1969 January 2; OHII 4 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 63 mins; Transcript Page Count: 13 pages
    Ives, Brewster
- Ives, Charles
  - Ives, Charles, 1905 May 27; OHII v1
    Ives, Charles, 1874-1954
- Ives, Chester
  - Ives, Chester, 1969 July 5; OHII 10 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 64 mins; Transcript Page Count: 39 pages
    Scope and Contents
    Interview Location Darian, CT
    Ives, Chester
- Ives, Richard
  - Ives, Richard, 1969 February 6; OHII 11 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 30 mins; Transcript Page Count: 17 pages
    Ives, Richard
- Ives Vocal Marathon
  - Ives Vocal Marathon, 2009 January 30; OHII 61 a-c; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.); Bruce, Neely; 3 Computer Files; 1.17 gigabytes; Approximate running time: 120 mins
    General
    Recording of a panel discussion from the Ives Vocal Marathon, a 2-day festival of recitals of the songs of Charles Ives. Panel entitled "Composers and Ives: Varying Responses to his Vocal Legacy" with Ron Kuivila, Chair and panelists John Luther Adams, Anthony Braxton, and Martin Bresnick.
    Festival location
    Middletown, CT
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    .wav files
    As a preservation measure, original computer files may not be used. Digital access copies must be provided for use.
- Kauffman, Charles H.
  - Kauffman, Charles H., 1969 June 25; OHII 15 a-c; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 97 mins; Transcript Page Count: 73 pages
    Brookfield Centre, CT
    Kauffman, Charles Henry, 1890-1976
- Kirkpatrick, John
  - Kirkpatrick, John, 1970 February 6; OHII 32 a-d; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 120 mins
    Kirkpatrick, John, 1905-1991
  - Kirkpatrick, John, 1970 February 18; OHII 32 e-f; Approximate Running Time: 137 mins; Transcript Page Count: 27 pages
  - Kirkpatrick, John, 1974 December 14; OHII 32 g1-g2; Approximate Running Time: 80 mins
    Kirkpatrick, John M.
  - Kirkpatrick, John, 1976 April 21; OHII 32 h
  - Kirkpatrick, John, 1971 October 19; OHII 32 i-k; Approximate Running Time: 106 mins
    Ives Class - First Violin Sonata
- La Pine, A.J.
  - La Pine, A.J., 1969 June 30; OHII 16 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 32 mins; Transcript Page Count: 31 pages
    Bethel, CT
    La Pine, A.J.
- Langinger, Herman
  - Langinger, Herman, 1975 March 1; OHII 60 a; Perlis, Vivian; Transcript Page Count: 25 pages
    Los Angeles, CA
    Langinger, Herman
  - Langinger, Herman, 1977 January 15; OHII 60 b; Perlis, Vivian; Transcript Page Count: 15 pages
- Leduc, Monique Schmitz
  - Leduc, Monique Schmitz, 1971 May 18; OHII 52 a-c; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 126 mins; Transcript Page Count: 81 pages
    Montreal, Canada
    Leduc, Monique Schmitz-
- Lieberson, Goddard
  - Lieberson, Goddard, 1969 October 23; OHII 28 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 32 mins; Transcript Page Count: 18 pages
    Lieberson, Goddard, 1911-1977
- MacKenzie, Findlay (and Barbara)
  - MacKenzie, Findlay (and Barbara), 1971 October 28; OHII 54 a-c; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 95 mins; Transcript Page Count: 38 pages
    Croton-on-Hudson, NY
    MacKenzie, Findlay; MacKenzie, Barbara, 1903-1975
- Meeker, Debby
  - Meeker, Debby, 1969 September 24; OHII 25 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 29 mins; Transcript Page Count: 23 pages
    Washington, CT
    Meeker, Debby
- Moross, Jerome
  - Moross, Jerome, 1969 September 19; OHII 22 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 32 mins; Transcript Page Count: 22 pages
    Moross, Jerome, 1913-1983
- Myrick, Julian S.
  - Myrick, Julian S., 1968 October 14; OHII 1 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 48 mins; Transcript Page Count: 24 pages
    Myrick, Julian S. (Julian Southall), 1880-1969
  - Myrick, Julian S., 1968 November 4; OHII 1 b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 28 mins; Transcript Page Count: 1 page
  - Myrick, Julian S., 1968 December 11; OHII 1 c; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 32 mins; Transcript Page Count: 19 pages
- Nikoloric, Mrs. Artur
  - Nikoloric, Mrs. Artur, 1971 January 29; OHII 46 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 31 mins
    Kenwood, MD
    Nikoloric, Margaret, 1885-1974
- Pickhardt, Mary Richard
  - Pickhardt, Mary Richard, 1969 September 24; OHII 24 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 30 mins; Transcript Page Count: 23 pages
    Pickhardt, Mary Richard
- Roberts, George
  - Roberts, George, 1969 June 16; OHII 12 a-b; Maas, Martha, 1934-; Approximate Running Time: 66 mins; Transcript Page Count: 32 pages
    Northport, L.I., NY
    Roberts, George
- Roberts, Mrs. George
  - Roberts, Mrs. George, 1969 June 16; OHII 13 a; Maas, Martha, 1934-; Approximate Running Time: 33 mins; Transcript Page Count: 15 pages
    Roberts, Eleanor
- Rudhyar, Dane
  - Rudhyar, Dane, 1970 March 18; OHII 35 a-c; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 90 mins; Transcript Page Count: 42 pages
    San Jacinto, CA
    Rudhyar, Dane, 1895-1985
- Ruggles, Carl
  - Ruggles, Carl, 1969 February 28; OHII 6 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 53 mins; Transcript Page Count: 20 pages
    Bennington, VT
    Ruggles, Carl, 1876-1971
- Ryder, Ely
  - Ryder, Ely, 1969 July 29; OHII 20 a; Maas, Martha, 1934-; Approximate Running Time: 13 mins; Transcript Page Count: 4 pages
    Brewster, NY
    Ryder, Ely M. T.
- Ryder, Will Mr. & Mrs
  - Ryder, Will Mr. & Mrs, 1969 October 9; OHII 26 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 62 mins; Transcript Page Count: 27 pages
    West Redding, CT
    Ryder, Will; Ryder, Luemily
- Sanford, Gertrude
  - Sanford, Gertrude, 1969 July 29; OHII 19 a; Maas, Martha, 1934-; Approximate Running Time: 32 mins; Transcript Page Count: 26 pages
    Sanford, Gertrude
- Seeger, Charles
  - Seeger, Charles, undated; OHII 34 a-c; Approximate Running Time: 130 mins
    SEE OH V #1 for all information
    Seeger, Charles, 1886-1979
- Sipprell, Clara
  - Sipprell, Clara, 1971 December 1; OHII 42 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 112 mins; Transcript Page Count: 61 pages
    Manchester, VT
    Sipprell, Clara E. (Clara Estelle), 1885-1975
- Slonimsky, Nicolas
  - Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1969 January 29; OHII 5 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 57 mins; Transcript Page Count: 20 pages
    Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1894-1995
- Smith, Eugene W.
  - Smith, Eugene W., 1973 July 6; OHII 57; Perlis, Vivian; Transcript Page Count: 1 pages
    Smith, Eugene W. (Eugene Waldo), 1905-
- Sunderland, Philip
  - Sunderland, Philip, 1968 November 7; OHII 3 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 32 mins; Transcript Page Count: 26 pages
    Sunderland, Philip
- Thompson, John S.
  - Thompson, John S., 1969 July 14; OHII 17 a-b; Maas, Martha, 1934-; Approximate Running Time: 65 mins; Transcript Page Count: 25 pages
    Providence, RI
    Thompson, John S.
- Twichell, Mrs. Burton
  - Twichell, Mrs. Burton, 1970 September 18; OHII 40 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 30 mins; Transcript Page Count: 21 pages
    Twichell, Katherine Eugenia Pratt, 1891-1981
- Tyler, Charles Ives
  - Tyler, Charles Ives, 1970 February 26; OHII 33 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 33 mins; Transcript Page Count: 15 pages
    Sheffield, MA
    Vivian Perlis
    Tyler, Charles Ives
- Tyler, George S.
  - Tyler, George S., 1969 March 18; OHII 8 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 32 mins; Transcript Page Count: 12 pages
    Tyler, George S.
- Untermeyer, Louis
  - Untermeyer, Louis, 1971 October 13; OHII 53 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 31 mins; Transcript Page Count: 24 pages
    Newton, CT
    Untermeyer, Louis, 1885-1977
- Valentine, Mrs. Rodman S.
  - Valentine, Mrs. Rodman S., 1971 March 23; OHII 49 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 62 mins; Transcript Page Count: 45 pages
    Refrigerio, TX
    Valentine, Christine Loring
- Van Wyck, Amelia
  - Van Wyck, Amelia, 1968 November 7; OHII 2 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 32 mins; Transcript Page Count: 20 pages
    Norwalk, CT
    Van Wyck, Amelia
  - Van Wyck, Amelia, 1968 November 21; OHII 2 c; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 65 mins; Transcript Page Count: 33 pages
- Verplanck, William Jr.
  - Verplanck, William Jr., 1971 March 25; OHII 50 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 31 mins; Transcript Page Count: 20 pages
    University of Tennesee, TN
    Verplanck, William, Jr.
- Verplanck, Mrs. William
  - Verplanck, Mrs. William, 1971 March 25; OHII 51 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 62 mins; Transcript Page Count: 47 pages
    Knoxville, TN
    Verplanck, Kathryn
- Wallop, Lucille Fletcher
  - Wallop, Lucille Fletcher, 1972 August 18; OHII 55 a-b; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 53 mins; Transcript Page Count: 14 pages
    Wallop, Lucille Fletcher
- Washburn, Watson
  - Washburn, Watson, 1969 April 18; OHII 9 a; Perlis, Vivian; Approximate Running Time: 33 mins; Transcript Page Count: 16 pages
    Washburn, Watson, 1894-